software engineering radio episode 9
remoting infrastructures part 1 and
listener feedback
[Music]
okay welcome to this new episode of
software engineering radio in this
episode Michele and Marcus will talk
about a panel language for implementing
remote communication frameworks a year
ago Michael Ovitz Doon and I wrote a
book on this topic it's called remoting
patterns and we basically cover the
patterns described in this book so the
idea is to explain how remoting
middleware things such as Carbaugh
dotnet remoting and web services how
they work internally and how they're
structured so why do you want to know
this you want to know this because it's
important to be able to use remote
communication middleware sensibly it's
important to understand principles
trade-offs and not just to know the
api's it's also important if you want to
optimize some of these middlewares if
you want to be able to set the right
parameters tune them and make sure you
can make performance optimized to use of
the middleware system and finally in
some circumstances you also have to
implement such a middleware yourself
because the available middleware systems
don't fulfill some non-functional
requirements for example if you're
deeply embedded and you don't have many
resources you might want to put your own
RPC broker infrastructure rank you have
to know how this looks like and the
patterns we are going to explain in this
episode will help you in doing so so the
need for remote communication and then
therefore the need for remote
communication middleware is motivated by
the existence of distributed computer
systems firstly because of remote user
interaction imagine you have a web
client and you need to interact with any
server web server secondly because of
system integration because you have
already multiple computers distributed
in a network and they need to exchange
data with each other and thirdly because
of non-functional requirements such as
scalability availability and fault
tolerance I'm sure there are even more
reasons imagine a web shop that gets
access by thousands of ng
users concurrently but only several
instances off the shop running at
separate computer might be able to
handle such a high load so this is
basically like a physical limit of that
one computer reaches and you need to
distribute it across multiple computers
so that you have also a higher
availability in case one fails the whole
webshop does not fail we already
mentioned the term middleware so we use
the term remote communication frameworks
or remote communication middleware
interchangeably so what is a middleware
the idea of middleware is that it sits
between the low level operating system
and in this case specifically networking
infrastructure and your application code
so it isolates the concern of remote
communication so it makes sure it
transmits requests it adapts your
specific interfaces to - to the
middleware so if you if you want to
write an application that that uses
distributed computing resources for the
reasons Michael just explained then a
middleware shields you from for most of
the details of this remote communication
and provides you a nice and easy to use
API to access the remote objects or
services so if we talk about remote
procedure calls
what is our PC after all I mean I've
heard about systems that use the
standard called Carbaugh what is CORBA
I've also heard people say carb is dead
can can you first of all maybe briefly
explain carbon and then and then in that
way explain what remote procedure call
middleware is yeah Kaba stands for the
common object request broker
architecture it's basically a set of
api's with semantics that got
standardized by the object management
group and for which you can have
multiple implementations different
vendors and open source communities have
provided implementations for carbon most
common order programming languages Java
and C++
there are also implementations in other
programming languages there are
eight-hour mappings COBOL mappings so
also languages that are not typically
thought of if you talk about mainstream
distributed systems right so carbon
isn't dead I guess it's just not hyped
anymore cava is today used in
applications servers as the working tier
doing all the remote communication
inside the application server Island
yeah also in the embedded world
I learned that because resources are
becoming a bit cheaper even in the
embedded world carbon-based embedded
systems are becoming more and more
ubiquitous yeah that's true and also the
call by implementations got more
lightweight there is also a minimum
cover specification so that Kaba today
is used more and more in the NetID world
as you said because of the resources but
also because of the higher level of
abstraction that got introduced in the
past four to five years so before we go
on and leave carbide behind for now one
last question and Kaba was intended as a
standard for interoperable middleware
did that materialized is one or able to
talk to another or yeah Kaaba has a
standardized protocol on the network on
the wire and there were first some
difficulties and the implementations
weren't so compatible in the first years
but in the past I would say five two to
eight years had been very compatible and
no issues regarding mismatches and the
protocol layer there are also other
approaches or other tools besides koruba
that are used for remote procedure call
middleware do you want to elaborate a
bit on them
besides Koba there is also is the
internet communication engine
which got created by Mickey Henning
there is also net remoting around
there's Java RMI around remote method
invocations and for web services
implementation we picked Apache axes for
example in our book Apache axis is a
framework for web service development so
one thing that's discussed by the
community in in this context is that
more or less web service is taking over
the remote procedure call middleware
world and I think a couple of things
have to be said for that first of all
not all web service communication has
remote procedure call semantics there
are explicitly two styles of doing web
services one is called RPC style and the
other is called document style where the
RPC style has this yeah we call a remote
method semantics or style and the
document centric or document style
basically assumes that you adapt a more
message oriented approach where you
exchange business documents or data
structures between peers so if we
discuss web services in this episode
we're basically talking about the RPC
style web services so our web service
going to replace all existing middleware
I think this is a highly emotional topic
and we don't want to go too far into it
but from our opinion I guess it's fair
to say that we don't think that it will
replace all kinds of middleware it's
more like an integration protocol for
systems using different middleware
systems for example if you have an
enterprise in which you use some kind of
tip code based integration software on
the one hand side and for example karma
in another system then you can use web
services to bridge the Interop
interoperability gaps between those two
systems despite all the improvements in
performance for web services it's still
true that the XML parsing and a creation
of XML data structures is much more
work for the computer it requires much
more computing resources than using
small tuned protocols like for example I
up one thing that hasn't been achieved
yet is that there is no standardization
of the programming interface yet so if
you implement a web service using the
exes framework and you want to use the
same web service implementation with
another framework then your
implementation might not be compatible
you might have to adapt your
implementation although for example in
Java world there is of course all those
standards J's are whatever that define
how those interfaces have to look like
at least in the Java world remote
procedure calls are not the only
paradigm for distributed computing there
are also other styles one is for example
shared repository having a database
where all the distributed peers access
the common data trigger each other to
exchange data to build a distributed
system there's also the paradigm of
streaming basically we do streaming
which is a different kind of interaction
besides remote procedure calls and
another one is messaging systems of
course messaging systems are primarily
used for large-scale integration of
really big systems for example the
worldwide hotel reservation system or
the flight booking system as far as I
know they're all message oriented so we
don't cover message oriented systems in
this episode and also not in our book
there is a good coverage of this in the
enterprise integration patterns by Bobby
Wolfe and Craig or Hopi and we're
planning to to get Lego on the line for
an interview so we can talk about
messaging systems in detail with with
Gregor who who really knows what what to
say about this topic some smaller issues
or some points we want to make however
is that messaging systems are always
asynchronous so there is usually no
association between a request and reply
so you send a message it's delivered
just like an internet maybe through
several intermediaries and once it
arrives at the target its
accepted by the target and the target
starts processing the message and maybe
it sends an answer so you have to be
prepared to receive the reply message
asynchronously so it basically requires
a different style of programming it's
also possible to simulate messaging
middleware on top of RPC style
middleware and the other way around you
can also implement an RPC style
middleware on top of a messaging
middleware one could argue that if you
run core bar over the Internet then it
is just what happens but it's probably
not a good idea to call IP a messaging
middleware so but it's usually better to
design a middleware from scratch as a
messaging system or an RPG style
middleware because the trade-offs and
the implementation patterns are quite
different when I get asked on when to
use a messaging system and when to use
an RPC style system it's always kind of
a tough question
one common guideline that I give is use
a messaging system in case you have an
event-driven application when you have
state machines driving the application
logic and use an RPC style communication
when you have to integrate the result
into your regular control flow so when
you for example have to fetch data from
a remote host and you need result
immediately for the next computation
step the different styles of programming
as I just said with the event-driven
versus regular control flow have an
influence on the programming model and
the architecture therefore the selection
of the middleware has an influence on
the architecture and vice versa so when
you plan a new system you should think
about the middleware carefully when
selecting the architecture it's not true
to say that you know like messaging
systems are only used in really big
enterprise systems they're also used in
those event-driven embedded systems
especially in unreliable environments
when the nodes the computing nodes could
easily fail our pc style programming can
get quite cumbersome because usage of
timeouts retrials and you need to cope
then typically in the application logic
with that and that can make the
application logic quite complex ok and
just to get some of the terms straight
if we say that we use messaging in
embedded systems and of course we don't
talk about those big big messaging
systems like TIBCO Enterprise or IBM's
MQ series it's just the same programming
style in that you exchange events or or
messages but of course the
implementation in embedded systems is
much much different from from those
enterprise grade systems just to make
sure it sits straight so so in in the
book and also in this in this discussion
here will shortly introduce patterns
that form a pattern language so we
talked already about patterns and
pattern languages in episode 1 of
software engineering radio as it happens
it result was also mihail and and me so
just to really briefly restate what what
a pattern languages so a pattern is
basically a proven solution for us for a
problem that happens all the time in a
certain context so if you want to build
middleware then there are a number of
problems that you will always have when
building middleware systems and our
patterns try to help you to to solve
those problems in a proven way and a
pattern language is basically a set of
related patterns that build on each
other in our case the pattern language
helps you to step-by-step build a
remoting middleware infrastructure and
so what we're going to do in the in the
next I don't know minutes hours is to
step through the patterns that that tell
you how to build a remote email where we
not only reverse-engineered the existing
implementations but Marcus was actually
involved
than several implementations of
communication middleware and I was for
example involved in the development of
the Ace or acaba implementation and
open-source implementation so that's
important to say that that patterns also
our patterns are not something we made
up but it's rather a combination of
reverse engineering in our own
experience and that makes patterns quite
useful because they are not nice
theories but they're rather proven
things from practical work so before we
actually look at the at our detailed
pattern language I think it's important
to to give the big picture and the big
picture for remoting middleware is that
it basically follows the broker pattern
the broker pattern is something that's
quite well known and has been explained
in poza one I guess and the pattern
oriented software architecture Volume
one book by Frank Bushman and and the
other folks from Siemens and so the
broker pattern works the following way
you call something on one side the
message is being intercepted it Specter
packaged into something that can be
transported over a network then it's
followed it over the network to the
machine or the process where the server
or the recipient of the message works
and over there the message in is
interpreted and the method is called on
the target object and then the same
thing works for the way back the return
value of the operation on the server
side is being packaged into something
that can be serialized over the network
protocol and it's delivered back to the
client where the middleware calls up
into the application layer and and and
returns the result and what we'll do in
the next episode is that we'll explain
how all this stuff works in detail
before we do that however we want to
spend the rest of this episode
discussing some of the listener feedback
we got for our previous couple of
episodes we've got a lot of very
positive feedback for our podcast so
first of all thanks to all of you who
gave us positive feedback about what we
do here I'm not gonna read all those
mails saying yeah this was good work and
this is great and go on like that
because I think there is no point in in
reading all the positive comments
however what I want to do is take a look
at some of the suggestions for
improvement and also look at some of the
more funny comments so some of the
emails were regarding the fact that we
do this podcast in English although all
of the members of the team are actually
German and so Patrick wrote to us I
think that's quite funny he says the
most of you are definitely the most
experienced an outstanding software
engineers in Germany why does this
podcast have to be in English it's
ridiculous can't you just be proud of
yourself and make this the first
professional and serious software
engineering podcast in German language
and actually it was my idea to do this
in English and not in German we really
want to get the word out worldwide and
actually this seems to work quite well
because if I take a look at the download
statistics we can see that probably 80%
of our listeners are actually actually
not from Germany and that's great
another email in that same vein is the
one from Sven he says when I listened to
the first episode I found it also
strange to hear an English spoken
podcast with German or Spanish dialect
sue Babbage is extra actually the
dialect that I speak if I speak German
and the funny thing is if I did this
thing in German I would probably have to
speak Swedish even more so you would
probably have a harder time
understanding it even if your for
example if you're from northern Germany
so those folks north of the mine in
Germany should actually be happy that
we'll do this in English another email
was also funny it's a content aside this
podcast is noteworthy because it is a
German podcast conducted in English
their intro and outro outro music
seems singularly singularly German and
so since I didn't know what singularly
German meant I wrote back to the sky and
email and we discussed a bit about the
music and so anyway so the music is
actually something we got several emails
about so if you like the the music or
the style of the music you might want to
check out Henning Pauly's website he has
a band called chain
and the intro and the outro is actually
from an album called chain dot exe so
that's even a bit geeky the the album
title but that's not the reason why we
chose it actually really liked the music
and so so that was our choice another
piece of feedback with regards to the
music that we got from several people
was that the music is too loud and yeah
we turned the volume down although I
like the music we'll turn we turn the
volume down so in this episode and also
in the two previous episodes you should
have noticed that the volume of the
music has been turned down another thing
that somebody mentioned on a block I
think is that the folks doing this
podcast are probably somewhat more from
the Java side of the fence I'm not sure
that there is a fence between Java
and.net developers but yes true most of
us have more experience in the Java
world so in situations where we have to
come up with a spontaneous example
usually it's probably going to be from
the Java well however we really try to
make this podcast not in any way it's
Java specific and we'll we'll make sure
that we cover net topics in in a in a
sense it or generally non Java topics in
the write proportional so we have an
interview with an interesting person
from the c-sharp community in
preparation and also we're planning to
do a lot in the functional scripting
languages area so yes we are somewhat
Java biased but we try to avoid making
this Java specific as good as we can
although sometimes it's gonna crawl
through there was also some other
feedback that basically addressed the
level of prerequisites of the experience
level that we assumed of our listeners
so one comment was that software
engineering radio will probably not be
of any real interest to anyone except
software developers and yes that's true
that's the whole point it's not going to
be interesting for anyone except
software developers and hopefully it
will be it will be interesting for
software developers the email went on or
actually was a blog statement so the the
blog statement went on
again it ends with this podcast is
definitely not for the software beginner
and yes this is true we try to address
what we call the professional software
developer so people who do have some
experience or who are studying computer
science or software engineering so
people who have experience on the other
hand we don't want to make this an
expert's podcast so that nobody
understands what we are talking about so
what's really important for us is that
you give us feedback not just on the
topics you'd like to hear but also on
the depth or the level of detail that
you think is useful please let us know
what you think and I'll make an
announcement on this and at the end of
the show so we'll have some we have some
prizes for people who give us feedback
so anyway let us know what you think
about the level of detail and we can
adjust the level I guess to some extent
another piece of feedback was with
regards to a discussion forum so on the
website we do have the facility for you
to leave comments that everybody can
read but the guy who wrote this mail
actually suggested that we'd have a
discussion forum now I'm not sure that
this is very useful there are many
discussion forums on the web and adding
another one is probably not very useful
because we wouldn't probably attract
many people from those well-established
discussion forums such as the
server-side comm and to some extent we
can also discuss using the comments
facility however if you think that a
kind of specific discussion forum with
replies and threads and all that stuff
is useful then please let us know and we
can we will see what we can do so this
was the kind of general feedback we got
let's now move on to some more specific
things in this case suggestions for
future episodes for example I don't know
how to pronounce this name I'll try
quiet Araki I don't know sorry if it was
wrong
hi there I love soft engineering radio
also my dear can you look into doing a
show about threaded application design
and some of the design methodologies
used in industry specifically I was
wondering how this address testing and
the time to release moving from Singh
threat to multi-threaded and yeah this
is actually a really important topic
concurrency in general and we're
currently preparing at least two or
three episodes on this topic starting
with the basics and then going to some
quite involved things with regards to
building scalable servers we also are
talking to luminary on this topic with
regards to giving us an interview you
might wonder why I'm not mentioning
names in advance now you know getting
some of those kind of celebrities in the
IT world for an interview is always some
of a problem not because they don't want
but because they have a very busy
schedule so what we are not going to do
is announce an interview with somebody
before we actually recall it it because
they can always things can go wrong and
timing doesn't work and all kinds of
things so we have an interesting guy
planned for the topic concurrency and as
soon as we have it in in the can
basically we'll let you know and we'll
announce it but until then we're not
going to mention names another guy his
name is Nanak also suggested a couple of
topics or a general areas of interest
one was to discuss experiences basically
so like what was the experience in
running a project for example using the
RUP process or doing extreme programming
or other metaphors or processes or
methodologies so not just explaining
principles of software engineering as we
do it right now but also Tegeler tech
look at more experience related tools
this also includes topics such as we
used this topic this tool on the project
and it was good or it was bad and also
in that same spirit interview Joe
developer and dojo architect and get
insights from those people about what
they found useful which principles they
found useful which tools they found
useful which methodologies and yes we'll
add these kinds of things however I
think we'll first cover some of the
principles and then later in later
episodes look more towards an experience
or
approach although we do have some
episodes in the pipeline that are more
experience oriented tools is somewhat of
a problem because if it's a commercial
tool and we say it's great then
everybody says they're getting paid for
that so it looked it sounds like
advertisement and if it's bad tool and
it's commercial we'll probably gonna get
problems and if it's a bad tool and it's
an open-source tool then we probably
start a flame war so mmm discussing
tools is somewhat of a a topic that has
to handle it has been handled with care
I'm not saying that we're never going to
do this for example in the model driven
episode I mentioned the open
architecture where code generator but
still tools is a delicate issue and I
mean I'm not saying we're going to
ignore it but let's see how this turns
out I'm not we're not certainly not
going to do two reviews or anything like
that so some more feedback on possible
topics from Jeremy from Israel he
suggests three topics one is
benchmarking how to test and measure and
how to see through the marketing fluff
in commercial benchmarks yeah certainly
an interesting topic I'm not sure we can
actually talk about about this topic so
we might have to find external people to
interview on this topic but yeah we will
we've put it into the pipeline the
second topic images aspect-oriented
programming and yes this is of course a
very big topic and we will definitely
cover it again we have a cool interview
in the pipeline so stay tuned I'm not
going to mention names but that's going
to be interesting
the third thing he mentions is building
highly scalable servers considerations
and threading models i/o patterns and
yeah as I said this is basically in the
spirit of the concurrency thing and we
will cover that in upcoming episodes
probably not too far from here and I
also have other interview folks talked
to with regards to building scalable
internet systems so we'll definitely
address those topics we also got
feedback from a guy called Charles weir
and that's interesting for several
reasons first of all I know Charles for
quite a while from the patterns
conferences and I have
quite some respect for him so getting
positive feedback from him is is really
encouraging he says this is good stuff
I've listened to the to the lot and have
picked up quite a bit thank you
so this is really cool and also what's
interesting is that he gives us feedback
almost like in those patterns Writers
Workshop so first he starts with things
he likes and then he gives us
suggestions for improvement so two of
the things he likes is one is relaxed
format conversation interview style so I
think it's really important that there
is not just one person rambling around
like I do now in the feedback but rather
that there is this kind of questions and
answer thing that makes it much more
lively and the other thing he says he
likes the music a lot and of course he
says it could be a little quieter so I
don't have to turn it down and yeah we
did that
and so now suggestions for improvement
he says perhaps a little more on the
examples and examples that are less meta
um so yeah as you will see at the end of
part 2 of the remoting episode we did
add example specifically in this case
the discussing korba and.net remoting so
yeah will will add some more stuff in
the example area another very specific
comment he makes and that's interesting
and I think you should you should take a
look at that and he says on a practical
note your number one episode on patterns
references
Linda's patterns Almanac this is now out
of print but she's handed the content to
me and I spent a happy few evenings
scripting with Perl to produce a web
version it's at HTTP wwe.com slash
almanaque I'll put the URL into the show
notes so if you're interested in the
software patterns Almanac and you can't
get it as a book anymore
take a look at the URL so there it is in
online form and thanks to Charles for
actually making it available online so
now let's move on to the feedback on
specific technical topics or content we
discussed the first thing I'd like to
mention is feedback on the dependency
management episode from hairstyle you
may remember this name from the post one
book he was one of the coop
one of the Siemens guys and he says that
in our dependencies episode we basically
mixed two kinds of dependencies and that
is public official dependencies and
implementation dependencies for example
if a component offers a certain
interface then this is obviously a
public contract so other components can
call it
however in for required dependencies
like this component needs this other
interface to work it's not that easy
there might be public dependencies that
would result from a context diagram so
like this component needs access to some
other component or some other interface
because the whole purpose of this
component is to do something with the
data from that other component so that
is also a public required interface
however there are also kind of in
official dependencies like for example
if a component needs a connection to a
database or other resources that are
specific to the implementation of the
component and that stuff is not the same
thing so yes there is a dependency and
you should make it explicit but it's
different from officially advertised use
case driven specific functionality
specific dependency so it's probably
good to distinguish between dependencies
that are important from a structural or
architectural point of view and the
other dependencies that result from an
implementation decision and as a
consequence you might need certain
dependencies so Michael is not just
suggesting to remove those dependencies
but rather to distinguish between those
dependencies that are intentional
because it's driven by what the
component has to do and others that are
accidental that are necessary as a
consequence of the specific way how we
implement the component and I think this
is a really really good point and we
completely missed it so take this to
heart and and consider that having those
two different kinds of two different
kinds of dependencies there was also
feedback on our
scripting languages episode from spin I
don't know which swen it just suspend
although you can catch all of the arrows
usually caught by a compiler with unit
tests it's a big difference to have the
arrows automatically show up as you type
like in modern Java IDs instead of
always running tests additionally I
think tool support in general is a very
important thing unless the language is
statically typed or the IDE memorizes
runtime types it's impossible to have
good refactoring and code completion
support isn't it so this might be a very
strong argument so first of all since
alex was the guy who basically
contributed the content for the
scripting episode I'll read his reply
thanks Sven yes you're absolutely right
full support is so much easier with
aesthetically typed languages and tool
support is one of the key performance
factors in my opinion now that I'm used
to refactoring browsers I really hate to
program to program without one of them
on the other hand I think it might also
be a problem that we are just too much
used to implement these tools the way we
implement them now dynamic languages
offer a lot of other possibilities there
for example for method completion
intelligence
you don't need an ast in a static
language you could also simply just
instantiate the object you need and ask
it for its method names this way things
might be a lot easier to implement then
with static languages but some
interesting developments in this area in
the next few years and different kinds
of ideas should show up actually to get
a hint take a look at the better
Smalltalk environment Smalltalk has the
same problems it's also dynamic and it
is not only the first factoring browser
implemented it's also very powerful one
so I also like to add one comment to
that and that is that maybe refactoring
support is something you don't miss much
if you work in dynamic languages I don't
have too much experience with languages
like Ruby or Python but what I hear from
other folks using these languages is
that they don't really miss the
refactoring support so there must be
something that that compensates for that
and let's simply maybe wait for the
episode with Alexander and Tom who will
discuss the experiences of a Java
programmer who transferred to using PI
Ruby in a project and let's ask him what
he thinks about that and other comments
wants ven makes is I'm really looking
forward to the next episodes on
programming languages especially the one
about the new c-sharp features I don't
know why he thinks we'll have an episode
about the new c-sharp features but
actually as I said before we have
something in the pipeline and we will
have an episode on c-sharp 3.0 one final
thing that I found on forum discussing
the Ruby programming language they
discuss our podcast and they think it's
great and stuff and then at the end they
say they all seem to like Ruby quite a
bit and so there is the question who is
the sponsor and how much they pay for
the words Ruby and rails and actually
nobody pays us there are no sponsors and
certainly nobody from the Ruby community
we just seem to like the language and
there's obviously no money in that so
this concludes our reader reader our
listener feedback I'm still used to
writing stuff and not to doing this
audio thing so this concludes our
listener feedback and we really want to
get more feedback from you I think this
feedback is really important and so to
encourage you to give us more feedback
we have a prize so and the idea is that
everybody who gives us feedback in the
way I'll just explain will enter into a
drawing where we'll give away a book and
since in this episode we're talking
about remoting infrastructures the book
will be the remoting patterns book
written by Michael Ovitz tune in myself
so this will be the prize and what
you'll have to do is you have to give us
feedback on the software engineering
radio podcast so you have to give us
feedback by let's think by April 15th
and the ideas that you give us feedback
either about three topics you'd like to
hear in upcoming episodes or feedback
about three things you liked or you
didn't like in the past so give us three
constructive points of free feedback and
you will enter into the drawing for the
remoting pattern spoken and of course
the way to contact us is either to write
an email to team @ s e- radio net or
just simply leave a comment on our
comments facility @ s e- radio dotnet
and make sure that you leave enough
information so we know who you are and
make sure you we can send you the book
assuming you're the winner right so I
think this finishes this Kombi episode
of remoting infrastructure's remoting
patterns part 1 and listener feedback
and we'll add this listener feedback
kind of thing occasionally to give you
feedback about the feedback we got from
you so thanks for listening and see you
next time when we discussed the second
part of the reloading infrastructure
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning poly for providing the music as
well as lips and comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]